Okay, happy תענית Ta'anit Talmud Torah Day, I guess. It's actually raining
a little bit.
Now, what was that line on that?
Yeah, yeah, we'll talk later. Anyway, so we pick up on דף
כ"ב, Daf Kaf Beit, 22, and at the two dots, we're actually
ahead and it's a very short דף daf today.
So תנן התם, Tnan Hatam, about ten lines down, let's review what
we said. The משנה Mishna spoke about if an animal
had expelled some type of a clotting or clumps of blood that
we basically assumed that it is a fetus and a fetus that
had developed enough that it's considered a developed fetus, which the גמרא
Gemara before didn't tell us exactly how much that was, what that
stage of development was for animals as opposed to humans. And therefore,
the next animal that comes out is exempt from בכור. Bechor. Now,
what's with this? So if this actually were or might be a
fetus, then it is a בכור Bechor that hasn't been שחט, shachted,
so it's number one, it's a נבלה, Nevela, so you can't eat
it, but you can't even derive benefit from it because it's a
בכור, Bechor, and a בכור Bechor that has not been שחט, shachted,
also you can't derive benefit. I mean, so one that have been
שחט, shachted, even with a מום Mum you can eat it, but
without it being שחט, shachted, it has קדושה, Kedusha, it has sanctity,
and you can't derive benefit with it. So what do you do?
You bury it. Okay, that's the first statement of the גמרא Gemara
is that you bury it. But then the question is, well, then
it should communicate טומאה Tuma of נבלה Nevela if it's basically we're
considering it definitely or possibly a dead בכור, Bechor, it should have
טומאה. Tuma. And the גמרא Gemara said it did not have טומאה,
Tuma, and the גמרא Gemara said, well, the reason it does is
because although there's a fetus in there, it's mixed up with a
lot of stuff and it's בטל ברוב. Battel Berov. So that becomes
a very sort of fascinating scenario where we say the mother actually
did miscarry, did expel a fetus, but in terms of the object,
we cannot really say that the object is a fetus or the
fetus is present, it's בטל, Battel, and therefore the mother is exempt
from בכור, Bechor, but the fetus does not have to the next
animal, but the fetus does not have טומאה. Tuma. And then we
talked about a similar teaching about a case about a human miscarriage
where the fetus causes טומאה Tuma of מת Met of a corpse,
and the position of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who was it, of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that said that again, in case when it
might be dissolved and in mixed into the embryonic sac and it's
no longer sort of visible that it loses its identity and it's
בטל, Battel, and therefore it does not cause טומאה. Tuma. So the
mother has had a miscarriage, and for all the הלכה Halacha about
that about her טומאה, Tuma, about her having a child, for the
next baby being a בכור, Bechor, but the thing itself is not
considered a corpse.
Wait, wait, oh, wait, so the thing itself is not, but she's
טמאה Teme'a still?
Yeah, so one doesn't lead with the other.
Well, she actually did, that's what my point. The same way the
animal is exempt from בכור. Bechor. She actually did have a miscarriage
of a fetus, but in terms of the object, we cannot say
the object represents a fetus because it is mixed up and dissolved
and it is not sort of majority present. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on to say the following.
And by the way, one of the reasons that it is buried,
I should have said also, is in addition to the fact that
you can't benefit from it, is that then makes it clear that
the mother actually, that this actually was considered a birth and therefore
that the mother is exempt from בכורה, Bechora, what the גמרא Gemara
says is כדי לפרסמה שהיא נפטרה מן הבכורה. Kedai Lefarsama She-hi Nifterah
Min Ha-Bechora.
Yes, if
the human, if the mother gives a has a miscarriage, she's טמאה
Teme'a in the same way as if her miscarriage, she's טמאה Teme'a
for the 30 days or
what she's טמאה Teme'a for seven days or 14 days, seven days
or 14 days. Right, depending if it's a boy or a girl,
but since you don't know it's this, you play it safe.
Oh, so you do more?
Yeah, you do 14. If you don't know if it's a boy
or a girl, you do 14. Right, so anyway, right, okay, fine.
So now the גמרא Gemara says the following: תנן התם. Tnan Hatam.
We taught over there. Now we're going to look at sort of
similar cases of actually human miscarriage
and you'll see it's analogous, not exactly the same but there's some
analogy. So let's take a look about ten lines down on דף
כ"ב עמוד א', Daf Kaf Beit Amud Aleph, two dots: תנן התם.
Tnan Hatam. We taught over there in אהלות: Ohalot: אין לנפלים פתיחת
הקבר, Ein Lanefalim Petichet HaKever,
fetuses do not have an נפל Nefel really means like a miscarried
fetus, it's called it to be a miscarried, do not have an
opening of the grave, I'll explain that in a minute, עד שיאגילו
ראש כפיקה, Ad Sheyagilu Rosh KePika,
until their head has become a circle, has become spherical like a
פיקה. Pika. פיקה Pika is a type of a spinning like a
I think it's called a whorl, W-H-O-R-L, whatever, like a some type
of a thing that you would wind wool around or you'd wind
thread around and so again I don't know if anybody have a
picture, you have a picture there in the anyway, so it would
be some type of a like you know some anyway some type
of a like spool, spherical thing that you would that you'd wrap
wool around. Now, what is the significance of that? First of all,
the phrase פתיחת הקבר. Petichet HaKever. פתיחת הקבר Petichet HaKever means an
opening of the womb, but it's important to explain that what it
means is an opening it's specifically a phrase that is used when
it's a mis- Because then the womb essentially becomes that child's grave.
So it's actually referred to as the grave, the opening of the
grave when it's a miscarriage. Now what is the significance of the
opening of the womb? Well, there are two significant aspects. The one
being discussed here is that if there's a fetus inside the mother's
womb,
then if you have some and it's dead, okay, there was a
stillbirth, miscarriage, as long as something is inside a body, a human
body or an animal body, it is considered בלוע, baluah, swallowed up.
And it does not communicate טומאה tumah to the outside. So although
if there's a dead body somewhere in this room, even if it's
I don't know, locked in a safe or whatever, it causes טומאה
tumah to the whole room, but if it's inside a human body,
if it's actually in the mother's womb, it does not cause טומאה
tumah to things that are in this room. That's when it is
בלוע. baluah. However, as soon as we're in the process of childbirth
and the cervix is opening and that's the פתיחה, p'tichah, the opening
of the womb, but here the womb is being referred to as
the קבר kever because the child died, as soon as it opens
and it's in the process of coming out, so then even if
it hasn't come out, it's no longer considered בלוע, baluah, it's no
longer considered absorbed in the mother,
and therefore the whole everything in the room is טמא. tamei. So
that is the significance of the stage of פתיחת הקבר p'tichat hakever
which just means the cervix is dilated and that child is about
to come out, the dead fetus is about to come out.
What? It's not out but everything is still טמא. tamei.
It's not out but everything is טמא tamei because it's no longer
בלוע. baluah. Now I should also say, not directly relevant for this,
but it's a very important discussion that comes up in נדה Niddah
and very practical הלכה, Halachah, that there's a discussion in נדה Niddah
whether אפשר efshar or אי אפשר ee efshar לפתיחת הקבר l'p'tichat hakever
בלא דם. belo dam. Do we assume that when the cervix is
opening up for the child to come out that that definitely means
there will be some bleeding? And that's the question about whether the
woman becomes a נדה niddah even before childbirth at that moment when
the child is coming when the cervix has opened, and that has
relevance halachically for when a woman in childbirth is a נדה. niddah.
I just point it out because a sort of sad comment in
terms of how terminology gets adopted
in הלכה Halachah is that although in the גמרא Gemara פתיחת הקבר
p'tichat hakever refers only to cases of miscarriage, right, because the child
has been miscarried and you want to know when the cervix is
open and the child's coming out, it then gets applied this question
about, oh, when during childbirth is a woman טמא tamei or not,
do we say it's possible for פתיחת הקבר p'tichat hakever whether when
there's a פתיחת הקבר p'tichat hakever there will be blood or there
won't be blood? And then the sort of the womb is referred
to as a קבר kever even in a case of a live
birth. So that's a little ironic and sad and that's what happens
when that sort of theory gets applied to a different case. But
in the גמרא Gemara the phrase to refer to the womb as
a קבר kever is only in cases of an actual miscarriage and
a still or stillbirth. Bobby, you had a question? Okay. Are you
upset, Bobby? Okay.
המקום ינחם אותם. Hamakom yenachem otam. המקום ינחם אותם, Hamakom yenachem otam,
there you go. Okay, so that is the question about when it
is considered to open. Now it says that that does not have
relevance if the child has not yet come out until the fetus's
head is the size of this פיקה, pika, the size of this
spool. And we're going to discuss in a minute what the size
of the spool is. It's not exactly clear why the head needs
to be the size of the spool. Once the child has the
fetus is dead
and
the cervix is open, what should it matter how big the fetus
is? There's a question about how developed the fetus is in general
before 40 days or after 40 days, but that's not what's being
discussed here. What's being discussed here is whether it creates טומאה tumah
before it comes out. It could be when it comes out, of
course it'll be טמא, tamei, it's 40 days developed, but before it
comes out and the cervix is open, will it cause will that
consider to bring טומאה tumah into the room or not? And that's
only once the skull is a certain size. And the גמרא Gemara
never explains why that should matter. And I should actually say that
this משנה Mishnah where it occurs in its original location in אהלות
Ohalos does
can be and is interpreted by the ראשונים Rishonim there in a
very different way. That it's not the size of the skull matters
for whether the טומאה tumah goes out into the room, it's to
indicate other things like if a woman moved from one room to
another room, at what stage do we assume the cervix was open
and what determination would we make based on the size of the
fetus to try to figure out when you know when a certain
event occurred. That's how like the רמב"ם Rambam explains this. But the
way the גמרא Gemara is explaining it here for some reason is
that it matters how big the child is. I guess you would
have to say that if the child is of a certain size,
then you assume that once the cervix is open, you sort of
already see it in the process of birth more than if the
child is small. So if they're therefore once to a size and
you see it more in the process of birth, then we see
it as though it's no longer בלוע, baluah, but when it's a
smaller size we still see it as part of the mother until
it actually comes out. I would imagine you'd have to give some
explanation like that. But that is the relevance here. That the child
doesn't although it's dead inside of the mother's womb doesn't cause טומאה
tumah when the cervix. opens and if the head is a certain
size, then it causes טומאה tumah even before it comes out. Right.
And for everybody, it causes טומאה tumah once it comes out.
Once it comes out if it's forty days developed, it causes טומאה.
tumah. And if it's not forty
days developed, it can't cause טומאה. tumah.
So then no. Doesn't matter. The size of the head is only
assuming it is developed enough to be considered a having developed, meaning
the forty day line is critical for whether it will cause טומאה
tumah as a dead fetus.
Wait, so before forty days why do you need the size of
the head anyway?
That's what I'm saying. You don't need it for once the child
is out. You only need it for when the child is still
in the womb and the cervix is open, and whether you assume
that because that'll be that that's no longer considered absorbed in the
mother.
But you see it developed enough even before forty days?
No, I'm saying the opposite. It has to be forty days before
you can even talk of טומאה. tumah. Now the question is, so
once it comes out it'll definitely cause טומאה. tumah. Okay, but what
I'm talking about is what's in the mother's
womb after forty days, will it cause while it's considered בלוע, balua,
absorbed? Once the cervix is open it's not considered בלוע, balua, okay,
if in addition to the cervix being open the head is a
certain size.
See, but what I don't understand is why it matters. I know,
that's what I was trying to address. I'm saying if it's still
inside the mother, I don't understand how you can say that it's
considered like open and like out, if it's like still inside.
Well, that I think is the point, that maybe that is the
combination of that idea of the size of the head because then
you see it in the process of being born already, so that
makes it considered no longer not considered to be a part of
the mother.
But it's still inside, I mean it's not outside.
Right, I understand. So I think that's exactly part of what this
issue of the size of the head is coming to address. Okay,
let's take a look now. גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, says the גמרא Gemara like this. מאי כפיקה? Mai kepika? Now
what is this spool, meaning we know what a spool is but
there are different types of spools. אמר רב הונא כפיקה של צמר.
Amar Rav Huna: Kepika shel tzemer. Like one used for wool. Okay,
which was obviously apparently a different size than one used for linen.
אמר ליה חייא בר רב לרב הונא רבי פירש. Amar lei Chiya
bar Rav le-Rav Huna: Rebi peireish. רבי פירש Rebi peireish Rebi explained
this to me. של שסי או של ערב? Shel shesi o shel
erev? Is it a spool used for the warp or the woof?
Okay, now of course we all know the difference. I don't even
remember them. One is used for the basically that they the way
they make fabric is that they spread out strings on a
grid essentially and they have alternating strings and they lift it up
and then they throw the spool across and then you lower and
lift the other one up and then you throw the spool across.
Anyway, the ones that are on the grid are one of them
is the warp and the other is the woof. I keep on
forgetting which. And one of them is thicker. I think the ones
on the grid are thicker because they have to hold the tension
better. Anyway I don't remember. What's ערב? erev?
The ערב erev
is the is the thicker and they're the ones on the grid?
No,
that was the question.
To take.
Wait. The ערב erev is the one that you throw back and
forth.
והשסי המחזיקם את המסכת באריג. V'hashasi hamachazikam es hamaseches baarig.
Oh, the שסי shesi is the one on the grid.
Here it is. וחוטי שסי חזקים יותר v'chutei shesi chazakim yoser and
וחוטי שסי
חזקים יותר ודקים.
v'chutei
shesi chazakim yoser v'dakim.
Oh, so the ones on the grid are thinner but stronger. Okay,
and the one that's you're throwing back and forth is thicker, I
guess. Okay, so anyway, and that's the ערב erev which is the
woof I believe.
The warp is is small and the other the woof thread is
long.
Okay, good. Okay, we got it clear. So the ערב erev is
the woof and that's the one that you have to figure out
a mnemonic to remember, that's the one you throw back and forth,
that's the thicker one. So if that's the thicker one, the spool
is going to be bigger. So which type of a spool are
we talking about? The warp or the woof?
אמר ליה תניא בברייתא. Amar lei: Tanya b'braisa. פיקה של שסי, Pika
shel shesi, it's a debate. The spool of the warp, דברי רבי
מאיר. divrei Rebi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rebi Meir says. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rebi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda says: של ערב,
Shel erev, the woof. And that's in תוספתא אהלות Tosefta Ohalos directly
debating this משנה. Mishnah. So there's a debate which one it is.
רבי אליעזר בר צדוק אומר, Rebi Eliezer bar Tzadok omer, רבי אליעזר
בר צדוק Rebi Eliezer bar Tzadok has a third position, or not
about it's not about a spool. משיורו תפיפות. Misheyiru tefifos. When it
appears as תפיפות. tefifos. Okay, that's when this is considered to be
the fetus is considered to be the right size. So מאי תפיפות?
Mai tefifos? What is this תפיפות? tefifos? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
משום רבי אליעזר בר צדוק כך היו מפרשים בירושלים כפרידה שקורעת להטיל
מימיה.
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel mishum
Rebi Eliezer bar Tzadok: Kach hayu mefarshim bi-Yerushalayim: Kepreda shekora'as lehatil meimeha.
When a mule bends down in order to urinate. So then it's
crouching in a way that it's that that it's the opening to
the womb is is opened up from the outside, meaning and you
can sort of see in it. So רש״י Rashi says that and
that you sort of see if you're looking inside you can see
sort of ridges and bumps. So apparently that is somehow describing, it's
funny because that sort of describing the opening of the of the
of the opening to the uterus I mean it's from the outside,
it's the vaginal opening, but anyway
but here we're supposed to be describing the size of the fetus.
So it's it seems like it's describing something different. You have to
explain it somehow means that if you were to look inside what
it would look like there looking inside, not that it's pregnant but
just what it looks like, it's similar to what it would look
like. So if you're looking inside, you know, if the, if the
midwife were to be looking in during this fetus when it's being,
you know, that's, that's a stillborn, what it would look like. So
it has some similar type of an appearance that is the case
in when it's sufficient size to cause this טומאה. tuma. So that's
his opinion.
And then he says, I'm sorry, I didn't read the last line,
כניראת כפיקה מתוך פיקה. kenireit kepika mitoch pika. It looks almost like
a spool within a spool. So I'm not exactly I have no
idea what exactly they're describing, but somehow he says, you know, that
that it is an appearance that is similar to what it would
look like if somebody was looking inside of the womb of this,
you know, or the vaginal opening of this, of this donkey. Okay,
so that's what that's the size, fine. So anyway, and that's the
appearance. So that's what we have in terms of when this fetus
is considered to cause טומאה, tuma, not when it's considered to be
a corpse, but when even in the mother's womb and the cervix
is open, because of its size, why the size matters not clear,
but like I said, maybe that defines it as more in the
process of birth, then it brings טומאה tuma into the house. So
אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna says
שמעתי שתי פיקות, shamati shetei pikot, I heard that in הלכה halacha
there are two different we use two different types of spools as
measures for different things. What are they? אחת של שסי, achat shel
shesi, one, in some cases we use the size of a spool
of warp, ואחת של ערב, veachat shel erev, and sometimes of woof,
ואין לי לפרש, veein li lefareish, and I and I can't explain,
I don't know which is which, when we use one, when we
use the other. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, ki ata Rav Dimi
amar, רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he
said בשם רבי יוחנן, besheim Rabbi Yochanan, in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, שלוש פיקות שמעתי. shalosh pikot shamati. I heard that
there are three different types of spools that are used in different
halachic contexts. אחת של שסי ואחת של ערב, achat shel shesi veachat
shel erev, one of the warp, one of the woof, ואחת של
פיקה גדולה, veachat shel pika gedola, one this big type of a
spool של שקין shel saka'in that you use by sacks, ואין לי
לפרש. veein li lefareish. And I don't know, apparently it was some
type of a spool that they used, I don't know, it's like
a clinch or whatever to seal sacks, and I don't know what
הלכה halacha categories we use one or the other for. So now
the גמרא Gemara says כי אתא רבין, ki ata Ravin, רבין Ravin
came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, פירשה משמיה דרבי יוחנן. peirsha mishmeih
deRabbi Yochanan. So he also learned this from רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
but he got the second lesson. He heard not only that there
were three spools, but what their relevance was. So here's what he
said in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. של אשה כשל
שסי, shel isha keshel shesi, when it is a case of a
human woman giving birth and again this case about a stillbirth or
a miscarriage, and when does it bring טומאה tuma into the house
in the process of childbirth. There the fetus has to be, the
size of the head has to be the size of a spool
of warp, which is smaller. של בהמה, shel beheima, a you know
an animal like a cow, where obviously things are bigger. So and
you have a similar question, when would the dead animal in the
cow not not be considered בלועה belua now. How could that be?
That who cares if it's not בלועה, belua, right, a human baby
as soon as it's not בלועה, belua, a human corpse brings טומאה
tuma to everything in the house, but an animal corpse you have
to touch it or carry it. So here's a very fascinating הלכה.
halacha. Let's say the the shepherd or whatever the farmer whoever it
is that's have to dealing with this cow is helping it give
birth and is sticking his hand inside the womb to assist it
in childbirth. Now you might think that if his hand is in
the womb and is actually touching the fetus that he's considered טמא.
tamei. But the actual הלכה halacha is no, as long as that
fetus is still considered to be בלועה belua inside of the mother's
womb, even if he is touching it, he's not טמא. tamei. But
if the womb now of this cow, the cervix opened up and
this the head was a certain size, just like in the case
by the mother, it's no longer בלועה, belua, and therefore when he
touches it even inside of the animal, at that stage he is
טמא. tamei.
Does that apply to humans too, like the midwife? Yes, yes, yes.
Now so okay.
So therefore so by animals the size of the of the spool
of the head has to be a larger spool, woof. של
בהמה כשל ערב, shel beheima keshel erev,
so of an animal it has to be the size of a
spool of woof, which is larger.
Like a goat or something?
I don't know, but presumably we're talking about a cow. פיקה גדולה
של שקין, pika gedola shel saka'in,
now how about this big spool that was used for sack? So
what would be the story there? So that is כדתנן, kidtnan,
like we taught in the משנה, Mishna, it's actually both a משנה
Mishna it's really more of a תוספתא Tosefta in אהלות Ohalot but
a piece of this is in a משנה Mishna in אהלות. Ohalot.
So as we taught הגוש הבא מבית הפרס ומארץ העמים. hagush haba
mibeit hapras umei'eretz ha'amim.
Now there is a rabbinic טומאה. tuma. There's a rabbinic טומאה tuma
of things that are considered to be טמא tamei like they're טומאת
מת, tumat meit, which really don't have a dead body there. One
is the בית הפרס, beit hapras, which is a large field in
which there was a the used to be a grave and it
was the field was like plowed over. So there may be you
know bits of bone somewhere in the field, you don't know, whatever,
that's a בית הפרס. beit hapras. טומאת ארץ העמים tumat eretz ha'amim
is basically the land of חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So they took
the idea that you know chutz la'aretz was טמא tamei from a
metaphor to a הלכה. halacha. by saying that because that we have
to assume, you know, we don't know where particularly since it's majority
non-Jewish and where they buried their dead and how they buried their
dead and so on or you know who knows what it is,
it might have been other factors as well, but any land of
חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz creates טומאה tum'ah of like like a dead
body. Now that's not only if you walk into חוץ לארץ, Chutz
La'aretz, even if you bring ground from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz into
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, like the reverse of now when you put
a little of the ground of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael into the
coffin. So here if you bring ground from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that would be have a rabbinic טומאה
tum'ah as if it is טומאת מת. tum'as meis. Now how much
of that ground from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz or from this בית
הפרס beis hapras causes טומאה? tum'ah? Okay, because we don't say it's
an actual dead body, we're afraid maybe they're little pieces of chips
of bone or something of that nature.
So even if you've gone to this ground, you just brought it?
So there is a discussion about about ways in which you can
less about חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz more about בית הפרס beis hapras
that you might be able to be מטהר metaher a בית הפרס.
beis hapras. Okay anyway so it says like this, גוש הבא מבית
הפרס ומארץ העמים שיעורו כמה, Gush haba mibeis hapras um'eretz ha'amim shiuro
kamah, how much, כפיקה גדולה של שקין, kipikah gedolah shel sak'in, again
like this big spool used for sack, שהוא, shehu, which is the
same size כחותם המרצופים, kechosam hamartzufim, like the seal of a type
of a pottery vessel,
and רש"י Rashi says
that you know it would have like a type of a cover
on it which would come to a head like you know sort
of like a what is not like a pyramid what's it called
anyway something it comes to sort of a point at the top
and and at that point there is this there's a handle which
is essentially the size of this type of a spool.
Okay, כחותם המרצופים וישנה בצד העליון של מגופת החבית הלחמית, kechosam hamartzufim
v'yeshnah betzad ha'elyon shel magufas hachavis halachmis, and it is on I'm
sorry I was explaining the second phrase, it is the top part
of this seal of the of the barrels from that are these
לחמית Lachmi barrels, רש"י Rashi says from בית לחם. Beis Lechem. Okay
so anyway that size of that spool of sack which is also
the size of the top of the lid, like the handle of
the lid of these particular types of barrels, that's a much larger
size and that is for this issue about the dirt from חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz or the dirt from a בית הפרס. beis hapras.
Okay so so fine, רש"י Rashi by the way says as I
said before that the spool here by sack is not a spool
used for the thread for sacks, but it is actually some type
of a spool used to like cinch you know the top of
a sack, like some okay, so anyway so that's that's the size
there. Now we go on,
where were we? Okay. אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיא.
Amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi
Yehuda Nesi'ah. Okay now that we are done with that interesting digression
about I mean there they obviously parallel to our משנה mishna was
about a case of a miscarriage. So we're dealing with a miscarriage
and what we were focusing particularly on before the child has actually
come out at what stage does it cause טומאה. tum'ah. Now we're
going back to another aspect of our משנה mishna which was that
that the fetus that is discharged from this בהמה, behemah, so on
the one hand we say it's a fetus and the בהמה behemah
is exempt from what do you call it from בכור, bechor, but
on the other hand we say that because it's mixed in with
other stuff, then it's not considered to be like present and therefore
it doesn't cause טומאה. tum'ah. So now we're going to look at
that issue about some type of types of mixtures and when things
are considered present or not. So let's take a look. Yes Michael.
Yeah I've already kind of asked you a bit but I'm really
you know wondering about this. Like let's say you know in the
market in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael someone like you know gives you
a tomato that was grown in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz with a
little bit of dirt in it now it's in your tummy.
Well first of all you only have to worry if you're a
כהן. kohen. Okay so if you're not a כהן kohen you don't
have to worry at all. No fine, but I mean so to
what degree
let's you know what degree now when we I mean
I have to I mean these are not טומאות tumos that a
כהן kohen is מוזהר muzhar on because first of all they're not
even דאורייתא de'oraysa טומאות tumos and in general כהנים בזמן הזה kohanim
b'zman hazeh are not נזהר nizhar on טומאות tumos that are דרבנן,
de'rabbanan, so it really is pretty much limited to
a although although on the other hand the גמרא Gemara does talk
about כהנים kohanim asking whether they're allowed to go to חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz because of the טומאת ארץ העמים. tumas eretz ha'amim. Yeah
you know it's an interesting question I'll have to look it up
I never heard he has a I understand I understand it is
true in the גמרא Gemara that you know that that כהנים kohanim
would be נזהר nizhar from טומאת ארץ העמים tumas eretz ha'amim if
they lived in Israel not if they lived in חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz to what degree would it apply even in this case about
transported dirt? I mean I assume that it's a very very rare
occurrence. How often do you ever deal with a significant amount of
transported dirt? But I suppose like you're right if you bought fertilizer
that was made somewhere in a whatever big thing it's an interesting
question I'll have to see if it's discussed. I don't know the
answer off the top of my head. All right so the גמרא
Gemara says like this,
okay so now we're moving on to this extra issue of mixtures.
אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיא, Amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi
Yehuda Nesi'ah, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said in the name of
רבי יהודה נשיא Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah it's not רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi
Yehuda Hanasi, it's רבי יהודה נשיא's Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah grandson.
Okay, הלוקח ציר מעם הארץ. halokeach tzir me'am haaretz. If you buy
ציר, tzir, which is fish brine, from an עם הארץ. am haaretz.
עם הארץ Am haaretz here is somebody that is not scrupulous in
the laws of טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. Now again, that's not even
a bad thing per se in this case because you know, there
wasn't תרומה, trumah, there wasn't קדשים. kodshim. The issue about being scrupulous
about טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah was really only for people that were,
for their own religious purpose, for like a special religious purpose, eat
even their non-sanctified
food בטהרה. betaharah. Okay, so עם הארץ am haaretz we're not careful
about that. Now עם הארץ am haaretz had other problems which were
real הלכה halacha problems, like they weren't careful about תרומות ומעשרות trumot
umaasrot either. But here, it's not even something that is a real
הלכה halacha demand, but it's being scrupulous about טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah
in a world in which that's really not הלכהically halacha necessary. Anyway,
so they are, so you buy it from them and you are
scrupulous in טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. You want to eat your even
non-sanctified food בטהרה, betaharah, and you buy this brine, fish brine, and
you have to be concerned that it might have come in contact
with something טמא. tamei. So it says the following:
משיקו במים וטהור. meshiko bemayim vetahor. You dip it in a מקוה
mikveh and it's טהור. tahor. Now what does that mean משיקו במים?
meshiko bemayim? Normally you can purify vessels and humans, you cannot purify
food. The one exception to this is water. If water becomes טמא,
tamei, since a whole מקוה mikveh is water, what you can do
is you can put it in the מקוה mikveh and it becomes
like the מקוה mikveh water and that changes its identity and then
it becomes טהור. tahor. Of course there's a little problem if you
want to drink it, what do you want to do? Even if
it's a clean מקוה mikveh water, what are you going to, take
it out? How are you going to do it? So the way
you do it is, you put it in a vessel, like a
bottle, like a wine bottle, with a very narrow opening, and then
once the מקוה mikveh water covers up that opening of the bottle,
you know, then that is, then that connects to all the water,
obviously the water's right up to the top, it connects to all
the water in the bottle, and now everything is okay. Okay, so
that's how you, that's called משיקו במים. meshiko bemayim. So you have
this brine, he says you do this in the waters of a
מקוה mikveh and then it's okay. Even if it was טמא, tamei,
it became טהור. tahor. Now let's explain the significance. Yes, it's fish
brine, but we're going to see it's mixed with water. Okay, ממנפשך,
mimanafshach, make up your mind. Either way, אי מיא רובא נינהו, ei
maya ruba ninhu, if in this mixture, this fish brine, presumably that
contains some fish oils but also water, and we didn't know whether
the water was the majority or not. So אי מיא רובא, ei
maya ruba, if the water was
the
majority נינהו, ninhu, so כיוון דעביד להו השקה, keivan de'avid lehu hashakah,
once you do this sort of, you know, this,
like this kissing to the waters of the מקוה, mikveh,
then טהרי להו, taharei lehu, you've purified it. Okay, so if it's
basically the majority of water, the water is טמא, tamei, now you've
purified it. ואי רובא ציר נינהו, ve'ei ruba tzir ninhu, if the
majority of it is brine, now this trick of putting it in
the מקוה mikveh does not work with anything other than water. It
does not work with brine. So if the majority of it is
brine however, ואי רובא ציר נינהו, ve'ei ruba tzir ninhu, ציר לאו
בר קבולי טומאה הוא. tzir lav bar kabulei tumah hu. So brine
doesn't become טמא. tamei. Okay, brine is not considered to be, remember,
this is a little bit funny for us, but you know, the
גמרא Gemara considers certain types of liquids to have not, not real
הלכה halacha identity. Meaning, of course all types of foods are foods,
but fruit juices, for example, מי פירות mei peirot in the גמרא,
Gemara, might be like some very poor derivative of fruit and not
even really have any significance. Not even be considered to be a
food or a liquid or anything. And similarly by fish brine, considered
that זיעה בעלמא, zeiah be'alma, like sweat, like some type of, and
therefore, for, if it's just brine or the majority is brine, then
that's even not really considered a food. That's not because people don't
eat it, but because it like has no הלכה halacha significance. It's
just some weird derivative for טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. Oh, no, but
also for טומאת אוכלין, tumat ochlin, right? Yeah, exactly. So not, right,
not that it's kosher to eat. That we have a פסוק pasuk
that says fish brine from non-kosher fish are אסור. asur. Correct. So
that's an important distinction. And juices from non-kosher foods are also אסור.
asur. Fruits are also אסור. asur. Right, right. So thank you for
that clarification. But for טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetaharah, these really add, don't
have significance. I should say, by the way, this is parenthetically, but
there is actually a fascinating question about how much certain types of
liquid derivatives even for laws of כשרות kashrut are significant, like there
are opinions and I don't want to, when it comes to let's
say liquor on פסח, Pesach, which is really some type of a
thing made from, you know, water, you know, and evaporated, and grain,
etc. So some say that's חמץ גמור, chametz gamur, but some actually
say it might even be מותר. mutar. Okay, so there's like a
fascinating range of opinions, but we do have actually by non-kosher fish,
do we have a specific פסוק, pasuk, הטמאים, hatmeiyim, to include צירן
ורוטבן. tziran verotban. So that is like a very complicated and, you
know, not, not clear category, these things of different types of liquid
derivatives. Anyway, here we are saying for טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetaharah, this
fish brine cannot become טמא. tamei. So if the majority of it
is fish brine, where are we, ואי רובא ציר נינהו, ve'ei ruba
tzir ninhu, ציר לאו בר קבולי טומאה הוא, tzir lav bar kabulei
טומאה הוא tzir lav bar kabulei tumah hu, it wouldn't have become
טמא tamei in the first place. So מאי איכא, mai eika, what's
your concern? משום הנך מיעוטא דמיא, mishum hanach meyuta demaya, how about
the little bit, the minority of water? So we're going to say
it's 60% brine. It's 40 percent water. Now that water presumably this
עם הארץ am ha-aretz came in contact with before he mixed it
in, and therefore it became טמא. tamei. So you have 40 percent
water טמא tamei mixed up with this fish brine. Now you can't
put it in a מקוה mikveh because since the water is the
minority—this is why it ties into our משנה, mishnah, right? It's about
majority, minority, and identity and so on—since the water is the minority,
it's not like it's present. So by putting it into the מקוה,
mikveh, it won't become טהור. tahor. But if it's not present, why
do I care about it? It's not present. So here we're going
to say, why am I care about it? ואי משום דמיא, הא
נתבטלו ברובא. Ve-i mishum demaya, ha nitbatelu be-rubba. Those are nullified. So
the same way you can't put the minority of water into the
מקוה, mikveh, it's not present, so it's okay, it's not present and
it doesn't cause you any problems. So now we get into an
interesting question how we can make the non-present water to become present
again, to wake it up. Let's take a look. אמר רבי ירמיה.
Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah. So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah said, לא שנו אלא
לטבול בהן פיתו. Lo shanu ela litbol bahen pito. If you want
to use this fish brine that we're assuming is now טהור tahor
for the reasons we said, you can use it to dip your
bread into it. אבל לקדירה לא. Aval lekederah lo. You can't add
it to your pot where there's additional water. Why can't you add
it to your pot where there's additional water? Because he says like
this: לקדירה לא. lekederah lo. Why? מצא מינו וניעור. Matza mino ve-ne'or.
One kind found its other kind and it woke up, which means
what? So in the scenario that was 40 percent water, that water
because it wasn't considered present when you put it in the מקוה
mikveh did not become טהור. tahor. So you have 40 percent water
here that was טמא tamei but wasn't present because it was the
minority. But now you put it into a pot of water. Now
the total amount of water content of this mixture is the majority
against the brine. So that water that was nullified
now again wakes up, it once again reasserts its presence, and that
was טמא. tamei. So now you've got טמא tamei water mixed up
in your pot and you have a problem. So this is the
phrase of מצא מינו וניעור. matza mino ve-ne'or. Now first of all,
it's like I always think that that's like a great example about
like in a classroom. If you have two kids or whatever, if
you sit them separate from one another, they'll be quiet. But if
you put them next to each other, מצא מינו וניעור. matza mino
ve-ne'or.
So sometimes the power of bringing two types of things together. Anyway,
but for ביטול bittul purposes, what's important is it raises an interesting
question about how we conceptualize ביטול, bittul, what it means to be
nullified in a mixture. One way to conceptualize it is like the
thing is here but it lost its הלכה halakhah status. Let's take
a case of like
חזיר chazir juice that was mixed up into chicken soup. So is
it that I don't have חזיר chazir at all, or is it
that I have it but it's not אסור assur because its הלכה
halakhah status is defined by the majority? When you say something finds
its kind and wakes up, in my mind that's a lot easier
to say if you said the thing was always here but it
lost its הלכה halakhah status. Then when it once now is in
the majority, then its הלכה halakhah status can sort of be reawakened.
If you actually said that right now because it's the minority it
stopped existing—there's no longer water, it's just brine—so if it stopped existing,
how does it come to
re-exist after it went out of existence? So in my mind, this
principle of מצא מינו וניעור matza mino ve-ne'or is important because it
certainly heavily suggests one way of thinking about ביטול, bittul, which is
sort of negating the הלכה halakhah status, rather than a more radical
way, which is actually considered to negate the whole thing stopped existing.
There are—I mean, well, this is a question—what?
Well, that's a question also, let's say it's drip by drip. I
have to get my head back into קדשים. kodashim. But that is
a very important conceptual model which has implications. I can't right now
fully process that. But that is anyway, but that is I think
an important... another waters...
so it carries its dormant טומאה tumah state.
It was water that was טמא tamei is now not טמא tamei
because it's been... because the majority here is non-water. And that negates
the status. But the status is like negated, not like, not like
completely expunged. Right. It's overridden, it's not expunged.
Indeed it's just water, so it carries the טומאה tumah state.
No, no, no. No, it is water. It negates its status of
טמא tamei is what I'm saying.
And then when it touches more water, then because it becomes...
yeah. So that's—I know you could say even with that approach, you
could say how could a state that was בטל batel reawaken?
I would say it carries dormant טומאה tumah the whole time.
Without being water? A dormant, maybe, yes. Okay, yes, it could be
dormant. But the point is, again, those are things that are possible
if you acknowledge that the water is here. I think the first
step in all of this is saying that you have to... you
can't say that the water stopped existing and then re-existed. That's, in
my mind, much harder. So this is pretty indicative of one way
of thinking about the קדשים kodashim issue.
Yes, fish brine, you know, it was 40 percent water into the
מקוה, mikveh, you haven't done anything because...
right, because the act of putting it in the מקוה mikveh did
not relate to the water at that stage. The water did not
have its own identity. And therefore the טומאה tumah was not removed
because at that stage the טומאה tumah wasn't even present. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara says like this: says a. So יתיב רב
דימי וקאמר ליה להאי שמעתא. yosiv rav dimi veka amar leh lehai
shmaita. So רב דימי Rav Dimi was sitting and telling over this
discussion. So אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye said to
him, וכי טומאה שביטלה חזרה וניעורה? vekhi tumah shebatlah chazra veniorah? So
he doesn't like it even in terms of the halakhic stage, right?
We said that maybe the physical reality can't reawaken. He doesn't like
it in terms of the halakhic stage. And the טומאה tumah that
was wiped away, how does that come back? Okay, once the טומאה
tumah stopped, it doesn't—you don't make טומאה tumah out of thin air.
So he does not like this principle of חוזר וניעור chozer venior
reawakens up again. אמר ליה, amar leh, so רב דימי Rav Dimi
says to him, ואת לא תסברא, veat lo tisbera, you don't buy
this? והתנן, vehatnan, we taught in a משנה: mishnah: סאה תרומה טמאה
שנפלה למאה—ha, seah terumah tmeiah shenafelah lemeiah I see why today's דף
daf is so short—שנפלה למאה חולין. shenafelah lemeiah chulin.
So you have one סאה seah of תרומה, terumah, of תרומה טמאה,
terumah tmeiah, that falls into a hundred of חולין, chulin, which is
טהור. tahor. Now, תרומה terumah that falls into חולין chulin is בטל
batel one in a hundred. So if it was just תרומה terumah
that fell into חולין, chulin, one in a hundred, the הלכה halakhah
would be that the תרומה terumah is בטל. batel. But there's another
הלכה halakhah which is that you have to give one—so because normally
תרומה terumah goes to a כהן, kohen, and so sort of not
to cheat out the כהן, kohen, even though it's בטל, batel, you
would separate out one unit and you'd give it to a כהן.
kohen. That's if everything was טהור. tahor. It would be בטל, batel,
but you'd give a unit to a כהן. kohen. Now here, you
might not have to give the unit to the כהן kohen because
since it's תרומה טמאה, terumah tmeiah, תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah can't be
used by a כהן kohen anyway. Okay, and our concern here right
now is not the one that you give to the כהן, kohen,
our concern right now is the issue about nullifying this that makes
up—from a תרומה terumah perspective it's nullified, but now we also it
is טמאה תרומה, tmeiah terumah, טהור חולין, tahor chulin, and we have
to worry about a טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah question as well, like
we've been talking about right now, so that's why it's relevant. Will
טומאה tumah be able to go away and come back? By the
way, if you want to know why today's דף daf is so
short, and we have this huge תוספות, Tosafot, because תוספות Tosafot is
trying to reconcile all the different discussions in the גמרא, Gemara, whether
we say things are חוזר וניעור chozer venior or not חוזר וניעור.
lo chozer venior. Do things wake up again once they find their
own kind or not? Distinguishes between many different scenarios. Scenarios between first
of all, you know, are you starting by adding the היתר heter
to the איסור issur or the איסור issur to the היתר? heter?
Are you doing it drop by drop, or are you doing it
in one large large sort of mixture? Depends on the הלכה halakhic
category we're dealing with—are we dealing with יין נסך, yayin nesech, which
is stricter, other types of איסורים? issurim? Are we dealing with something
that goes by a משהו, mashehu, even the tiniest amount, or by
taste? All of these are various issues that תוספות Tosafot is working
through to figure out the parameters of when you say something reawakens.
Okay, but that gives us a very short דף daf today. So
let's keep on going. So this one unit of תרומה טמאה terumah
tmeiah fell into a hundred units of
חולין. chulin. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, תירקב, tirakev, take one
unit out and let that unit rot, because that unit represents the
תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah and you can't benefit from תרומה טמאה. terumah
tmeiah. תוספות Tosafot adds that you really can't benefit while you're burning
it, fine, תוספות Tosafot tries to figure that out, let's not worry
about that. You treat that unit as the תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah
and you let it rot. שאני אומר היא סאה שנפלה היא סאה
שעלתה. sheani omer hi seah shenafelah hi seah shealtah. The one that
fell in is the one that you took out. Okay, very convenient
assumption, but the reason you're allowed to make this convenient assumption is
because in principle it's already בטל, batel, it's one in a hundred.
Okay, why he demands that you do this, that's because normally by
תרומה terumah anyway we demand you take one out to give it
to a כהן. kohen. Here even though the כהן kohen can't benefit
from it, you do it again, you assign it to this, and
therefore it's okay. That's what he says. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, תעלה.
taaleh. No, it's בטל, batel, you don't need to take anything out,
you don't even need to give something to a כהן kohen because
he can't really benefit, and it's one in a hundred. ותאכל, veteachel,
but you have to eat it in the following way: either
נקודיים—נקודיים is a phrase that means dry without getting any contact with
water—או קליות, o klayot, or roasted, but again don't get in contact
with water. Okay, או תלוש במי פירות. o telush bemei peirot. If
you want to make it into dough—this is all grain—use fruit juices
which don't make things susceptible to טומאה. tumah. You remember of course
that food has to come in contact with water to be susceptible.
Okay, the טהור חולין, tahor chulin, non-תרומה, terumah, has never come in
contact with water. So clearly the חכמים Chachamim are saying, look, from
a תרומה terumah perspective it's בטל, batel, but we're concerned from a
טומאה tumah perspective, okay, that this is טמא. tamei. And if you
go ahead and get the grain wet and susceptible, then the טמא
תרומה tmei terumah that's mixed up will make everything else טמא tamei
as well. Okay, now the point is who really cares? You're allowed
to eat חולין טמאים, chulin tmeiyim, but we'll see later what the
concern might be, or maybe you're a person that doesn't want to
eat חולין טמאים. chulin tmeiyim. תוספות Tosafot actually has an ingenious explanation.
תוספות Tosafot says that the תרומה terumah now is בטל, batel, but
once you make everything טמא, tamei, then the תרומה terumah somehow
reasserts its presence and then it's as if you also made the
תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah again. Anyway, whatever the issue might be, there's
somehow a concern that you don't want the rest of the—the rest
of everything else to become טמא. tamei. So keep it dry or
knead it with מי פירות. mei peirot. Or you say מי פירות
mei peirot no
significance—no, מי פירות mei peirot will not make it susceptible to טומאה.
tumah. או תתחלק לעיסות, o titchalek leisot, or separate it off into
different pieces of dough. make different breads with it and each bread
will not have enough that it can become טמא tamei *tamei*, even
if you want to use water, ובלבד שלא יהא במקום אחד כביצה
*uvilvad shelo yehei bemakom echad kebeitzah*, as long as there's not an
egg size in any one place.
Now why is that?
Well, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that the purpose of the egg
size here is not what you would have thought is that let's
say we said it's a ratio of one in a hundred, תוספות
Tosafot. *Tosafot* says what it really means is you cannot be making
dough with size of more of a hundred and one eggs. Why?
Because what it means is you don't want there to be a
ביצה *beitzah* of the טמא tamei, תרומה trumah *tamei trumah* in any
one place. So if you don't, because that would then communicate טומאה
tumah *tumah* to something else. So if you don't want a ביצה
*beitzah* of the טמא tamei. תרומה trumah *tamei trumah* in any one
place but the ratio's a hundred to one, you can have up
to a hundred ביצות *beitzot* in any one place, that size. That's
the way תוספות *Tosafot* explains it. Anyway, the point of all this
is all according to חכמים *Chachamim*. The point is so according to
רבי אליעזר Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer*, he acts as if we removed it.
And חכמים *Chachamim* say we're not removing it, but we have to
treat it as somehow present and therefore we have to be concerned
that it's not going to communicate טומאה tumah *tumah*. Now make up
your mind, if it's בטל batel *batel*, it's בטל batel, *batel*. Why
is this idea that it's בטל battel, *batel* but we don't want
it to be, the other, you know, things to become טמא tamei
*tamei* through it? So the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to ask that. ותני
עלה *V'tani ala*, we taught on this, אותן חולין chullin, לרבי אליעזר
מטילין עליהן *otan chullin le'Rabbi Eliezer matilin aleihen*, first he had a
ברייתא *braita* that said even according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* the
stuff you left behind, what do you do with the stuff you
left behind? Guess what, the exact same thing. יאכלו נקודיי *Yochlu nikuday*,
either eat it dry, או קליות *o kalyot* or roasted, או ילוש
במי פירות *o yalosh be'mei peirot* or use fruit juices to make
the dough, או תחלק עיסות ובלבד שלא יהא כביצה במקום אחד *o
techalek isos u'vilvad shelo yehei kebeitzah bemakom echad* or make separate doughs
but don't have a כביצה *kebeitzah*. So even רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
says the dough left behind, we have to be concerned about the
טמא tamei תרומה trumah *tamei trumah* that will be מטמא *metamei*. So
now the question of all this is, I don't get it. You
just said it's בטל battel. *batel*, why are you so concerned about
טומאה tumah *tumah*, what's going on here? So the גמרא *Gemara* says
we treat תרומה trumah *trumah* in a higher standard.
But תרומה terumah *trumah*'s בטל *batel*, so we're going to be more
consider it present because of טומאה tumah *tumah* than because of תרומה
*trumah*? I mean, תרומה טמאה trumah tmayah *trumah tmeia* is a pretty
serious thing. So let's take a look at what the גמרא *Gemara*
says. ואמר עולא מה טעם ta'am *V'amar Ulla mah ta'am*, what's the
reason for all of this? For רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and חכמים
*Chachamim*, why do we care about טומאה tumah *tumah* if the thing
was already בטל *batel*? So what's the reason? גזירה שמא יביא קב
kav חולין טמאין ממקום אחר וקב ועוד ממין זה vekav veod mimin
zeh, *Gezeirah shema yavi kav chullin tmei'im mimakom acher ve'kav ve'od mimin
zeh*, that you're going to just have your, you know, קב kav
*kav*, whatever it is, your gallon of טמא tamei, *tamei* grain, not
תרומה *trumah*, טמא tamei, *tamei* grain and you want to make it
טהור tahor *tahor*. So the way you're going to make it טהור
tahor *tahor* is you're going to mix it with טהור tahor. *tahor*
grain that's not susceptible, that's a majority, and you'll mix it all
together, the majority you'll be טהור tahor, *tahor*, that'll make it go
out of its identity, that'll make it טהור *tahor*. Now, two important
questions here. First of all, תוספות *Tosafot* says, I didn't think you're
allowed to intentionally mix things up, you know, in order to affect
ביטול bittul. *bitul*, right? אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה *Ein mevatlin issur le'chatchila*.
So תוספות *Tosafot* doesn't really have an answer to that except he
says we're afraid you're going to do it even though you're not
allowed. But an interesting thing to think about is maybe this is
not אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה *ein mevatlin issur le'chatchila*. There's really no
prohibition of eating חולין טמאין *chullin tmei'im*. Even if you are one
of the פרומער *frummer* people that eats the חולין בטהרה *chullin b'taharah*,
it is not objectively defined as a forbidden thing. So it's an
interesting to think of is it permissible to affect ביטול bitul *bitul*
if this is not something that's objectively problematic even though I personally
only eat my חולין בטהרה *chullin b'taharah*. That's something I'm suggesting תוספות
*Tosafot* didn't say that. But anyway, that's one issue. The other issue
to mention that I should have mentioned until now that I didn't
is why here are we going by majority? Right? Because he says
you'll take your one קב *kav* of טמא tamei חולין *tamei chullin*
and you'll mix it with a קב *kav* plus a unit plus
a little bit and it'll be a majority. Don't we normally need
like sixty times? So תוספות *Tosafot* actually says, you know, and why
by like all these cases, by the fetus and all the cases
we started with, we've just been talking about majority. So תוספות *Tosafot*
said the need of sixty times is when you're dealing in the
world of non-kosher food. And there what matters is taste. And we
say that more than a sixtieth might have taste. When you're dealing
in other areas, we don't necessarily use taste as the criteria or
sixtieth as the criteria and maybe the majority sometimes could be enough.
And that's why by this case of the fetus or the ברייתא
*braita*, even though it's food, right, but it's about the world of
טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah ve'taharah*. It's not about the world of non-kosher
food. And therefore majority might be more significant, is what is mostly
is it's what's what is primarily significant. So now what do we
afraid of? You've got this grain that תרומה טמאה *trumah tmeia* was
mixed up or whatever. You're going to consider it totally טהור *tahor*
now. I have some other grain in my house that's טמא tamei,
*tamei*, not תרומה *trumah*, and I want to make it טהור *tahor*.
So what am I going to do? Whether rightly or wrongly, you
know, whether I'm allowed to or not, I'm going to mix one
unit of that with a unit plus epsilon of the of this
mixture that I've got here and I'll mix it, it'll be a
majority and it'll all be טהור *tahor*. But now we got a
little problem. This mixture I have here does has not just pure
all טהור *tahor* grain here, it has one one-hundredth of it originated
in תרומה טמאה *trumah tmeia*, right? Remember that's what the scenario, one
one-hundredth originated in תרומה טמאה *trumah tmeia*. If I'm going to mix
it with טמא tamei, *tamei* grain, then it's going to be מצא
מין את מינו *matza min et mino*, right? The תרומה טמאה *trumah
tmeia* is going to be... Connect with other things that are טמא,
tamei that the טמא grain that I'm starting and rather than it
being this has one plus epsilon and this has one, the sides
will switch, it's the deciding vote. So the תרומה then joins with
the other stuff that's טמא, and that's the majority, and it does
not affect
ביטול. Okay? שמא יביא קב חולין טמאים ממקום אחר, Shema yavi kav
chullin tmeim mimakom acher, you'll bring one קב of חולין טמא chullin
tamei from a different place, וקב ועוד ממין זה, and a קב
and a little bit from this mixture. סבר, savar, you figured, אי
בטיל ברובא, i batil beruva, I'll negate the טומאה tumah, status of
this חולין טמא chullin tamei with the majority of this stuff. וכיון
דאיכא האי משהו, vekeivan deika hai mashehu, but because there's that one
percent or point nine percent of תרומה טמאה there, so מצא מין
את מינו ונעור, matza min et mino veneor, it'll wake up and
because it'll wake up, it'll transfer over to the other side. So
therefore, in order to remind you that there's potential טומאה tumah here,
we tell you, you can't get the rest of the grain susceptible,
you have to always remember that there's a tiny bit of טומאה
tumah תרומה here, and right, and that's why we give you all
these guidelines: don't get it wet, use מי פירות, mei perot, etc.
That way you'll know this is not pure טהור grain, this is
טהור grain with a little bit of potential טומאה tumah. in it.
Okay? And that's why you're protecting it from becoming טמא. So what
do you see though? Because to protect that scenario, that's why we
give you those guidelines, but that means that when that happens, this
thing that has been בטל will reawaken. So you see even by
טומאה tumah we say, even after it's negated, it can reawaken when
it finds its kind. So isn't that a proof that we do
say it reawakens? Why אביי Abaye did you have a problem with
that? So אמר ליה, amar lei, so אביי Abaye said
back, אם טומאה מעוררת טומאה טהרה מעוררת טומאה? im tumah meoreret tumah
taharah meoreret tumah? Says no no no, I agree that in principle
that it can find its kind and wake up, but in that
case they really are alike. It's טמא grain finding dormant טמא תרומה
grain. טומאה tumah. and טומאה, they're all exactly the same, that does
wake it up and now brings the תרומה back into being into
existence. But your case for the water and the fish brine, the
water in the fish brine was טמא, you were going to put
that with the water in your pot, which was טהור. So although
there it's water and water, that's not enough to wake it up,
it's not enough because it's not the exact same kind. Now that
did not sound, I should just say, like אביי's Abaye original objection.
אביי's Abaye original objection was, if the טומאה went away, how does
it reappear? Now he's admitting that that actually can happen. His objection
is not that something can reassert itself. His objection is what are
the conditions that you need for that to happen? It has to
be an exact same thing that it links to, not something that's
not exactly the same. Okay, so now even אביי Abaye does admit
in principle this thing can reawaken, and his only question and his
only question is what are the conditions? I should say personally that
I actually think that the case with the fish brine makes more
sense that it reawakens, because there it might be that they're different
in terms of one is טמא, one is טהור, but they're the
same in terms of their physical characteristics, right? That one is water
and the dormant water, you know, and that sort of in my
mind sort of more connects and reasserts the presence more. In this
case, it's all grain. The mixture was grain and grain, and it's
coming in contact with other grain. So what is considered to be
the like kind to reassert its presence? Is it physically the same
type of stuff, or is it the halakhically the same type? אביי
Abaye is saying to me, I want it to be the halakhically
similar, טומאה and טומאה. But I think you could see the very
strongly the other side, that says the other case is even more
obvious. There they're even physical, water and water, and that brings the
water reality back to the
surface. Yes, Tosh. No, that is a point, and we are assuming
here, we are assuming here like full mixtures, and by the grain
you could assume that we're talking about like flour, which allows for
like a full mixing of them. But I wasn't saying that. That
is a point as well, that by issues of mixtures, you have
to assess whether things are truly mixed and dispersed or not. But
the point I was making more was that one what's reasserting itself
is its water reality, physical reality, and that more becomes more of
a reality when it connects with other water. Whereas in this case,
there's no physical reality that's changing, it's all flour. But אביי Abaye
saying, oh, that I accept more because there's טומאה and טומאה. One
related point to this by the way, one of the important points
that this huge תוספות makes and that other ראשונים Rishonim make as
well is that even if normally we would not say something wakes
up again, we would certainly say it wakes up when the taste
now re-emerges. So let's say you had like drops of חזרת, chazaret,
here's an example, right? I have a little slow חזרת chazaret drip
into my chicken soup. Okay, so I can't taste it, so it's
בטל, right? And I can't taste it. So drip, drip, drip, drip.
So even if normally I would say I don't say something reawakens,
as it continues to drip, at a certain stage it's going to
taste like חזרת. chazaret. Okay, so there, when the taste reasserts itself,
everybody would have said that the thing reawakened. reasserts its identity and
reawakens. So what I'm, so the, and because טעם taste of forbidden
foods is problematic intrinsically, that certainly reasserts. So what I'm saying is
that to some degree that's true about the water in the water;
when the physical reality reasserts itself, it's more significant than the halachic
linking of טמא and טמא, but anyway for אביי, Abaye, he's willing
to concede this case but not the case of the fish brine
in the water. Yes, one last question.
Rabbi אליעזר, how come he's saying that you have to be strict
on these things in a row and then be strict on whatever's
left
over?
Well, that's a good question, presumably it could be just because he
wants this to be comparable to normal cases of תרומה getting mixed
up with חולין, which is we separate out a unit. So here
too, even though it's טמא, we separate out a unit.
But why worry about everything else once you've separated?
Because this is only a— we're only pretending as if this was
the right one, we really know that most likely it's not the
right one and most likely there's still some of the other stuff
mixed up. Okay, he's not denying that. Now that is normally בטל,
but when it comes together, the ביטול gets re-awakened. So he basically
admits, he just says that I'd rather it חומרא, chumra, more מחמיר,
machmir, like everybody agrees that it's basically בטל. He just wants it
to look good. Fine, it looks good, but even so the reality
is still the same reality, there's stuff that's still mixed up. Okay,
second time that we finished early and ahead.
We have to appreciate those large תוספות.
Yes, it seems there's an easy answer to the mixing of the
two mounds of flour, which is a lot less טמא flour than
it
is in the— the טהרה taharah can't mix with the
טהרה taharah flour.